salford.ac.uk 2018-10-08

# Data Protection, Privacy and Cookies | Data Protection, Privacy and Cookies | University of Salford, Manchester

Here at the University of Salford we work hard to ensure that you get the very best experience, whether you are a visitor, a student, a staff-member, alumni or partner, without having to worry if your information is safe.

Outlined below is how & why we collect, use, & share your personal information, & your rights in relation to that data.

We know that there’s lots of information here, but we want you to be fully informed – we hope the following sections will answer any questions you have but if not, please do get in touch with us.

## A bit about Us

The University of Salford is the “Data Controller” of your personal data & is subject to the data protection legislation & to the General Data Protection Regulation 2016 (“GDPR”). We are registered with the Information Commissioner’s Office (“ICO”) registration number Z469563X and our Data Protection Officer is Andrew Hartley.

## Privacy

We appreciate an individual’s right to privacy & in all situations we strive to achieve a balance between protecting that right & confirming that we have the correct information to ensure we can provide an exceptional experience for all.

Under the GDPR a number of new principles mean that individuals have greater rights concerning their information & how it is used (see Data Subject Rights) We have detailed an overview of these principles below & included the Privacy Statements for all groups of people who the University of Salford interact with.

The law on data protection sets out a number of different reasons for which an organisation may collect & process your personal data, including:

#### Public Task

To ensure that we meet carry out our role as an institute of higher education & provide our Students with required level of service we need to collect & process relevant personal data.

For example, when we record your academic results & validate with your previous Further Education provider.

#### Consent

In specific situations, we can collect & process your data with your consent.

For example, if you are a Graduate and you tick a box to receive email enquiring if you wish to become a donor.

#### Contract

In certain circumstances, we need your personal data to comply with our contractual obligations.

For example, when you accept a place at the University we need to capture certain information in order to provide you with the place & service.

#### Legal compliance

If the law requires us to, we may need to collect & process your data.

For example, certain government departments need us to collect and pass on statistical data.

#### Legitimate interest

In specific situations, we require your data to pursue our legitimate interests in a way which might reasonably be expected as part of running the University which does not materially impact your rights, freedom or interests.

For example, after you graduate, we will send you email newsletters updating you on what is happening here at the University.

When collecting your personal data, we’ll always make clear which data is necessary in connection with a particular service.

Here are some examples of when we collect your information, for further details please take a look at the relevant Privacy Policy.

  * When you visit our website
  * When you engage with us on social media
  * If you join us as a Student or Staff member we need to capture data in order to enter into a contract with you
  * If your image is captured on the CCTV that we deploy across our sites for safety & security
  * When a donation or a purchase is made
  * When an individual attends a clinic run by one of the University Schools

Under the GDPR we are only permitted to collect the minimum amount of information needed to carry out a specific purpose, therefore depending on your relationship with us we collect different amounts of data.

Example, if you are making a decision about university choices & want some information sending to you we would only take your name & contact details (address & email) but if you are joining us as a member of Staff we would need more information, such as date of birth, gender, financial details.

If your relationship with us changes, we remove all unnecessary information that we hold on you.

Example, after Graduation, when you become an Alumni, we no longer need information on attendance or financial details so we will delete these & only retain details that enable us to perform Alumni activity, such as contact details, information on your degree, when you attended the University & details that help us shape our Alumni programme.

Different information is processed for different purposes, some of it is used to improve experience, such as Cookies on the website & other information helps us track performance, comply with legislation or help keep you informed of what is happening here at the University of Salford.

Detailed information about how we use information for different purposes can be found in the relevant Privacy Policies, but here are some examples:

  * Website Cookies tell us which pages you find useful, & therefore how we can improve your experience online
  * We collect & report upon sensitive personal data, such as gender, ethic origin & disability data in order to undertake equal opportunity monitoring
  * We require financial data to administer financial activity, such as fees, scholarships & bursaries
  * We take photographs in order to issue Access Passes
  * Information captured during Research projects will be processed in order to develop our programmes & insight

Data is retained for as long as it is required to perform its purpose, or for as long as is required by law. At the end of that retention period, your data will either be deleted completely or anonymised, for example by aggregation with other data so that it can be used in a non-identifiable way for statistical analysis & business planning.

Sometimes we share your personal data with trusted third parties, in order to meet our contractual needs or to improve our services.

Here’s the policy we apply to those organisations to keep your data safe & protect your privacy:

  * We provide only the information they need to perform their specific services
  * They may only use your data for the exact purposes we specify in our contract with them
  * We work closely with them to ensure that your privacy is respected & protected at all times
  * If we stop using their services, all of your data held by them will either be deleted or rendered anonymous

Examples of the kind of third parties we work with are:

  * IT companies who support our website & other business systems.
  * Operational companies such as the Students Loan Company
  * Direct marketing companies who help us manage our electronic communications with you
  * Google Analytics to understand our website usage, this is subject to acceptance of Cookies on our websites. See our [Cookies Notice](https://www.salford.ac.uk/privacy#section3), below, for details
  * Clinical practices providing health & well-being services

Whenever you have given us your consent to use your personal data, you have the right to change your mind at any time & withdraw that consent.

You have the right to stop the use of your personal data for direct marketing activity through all channels, or selected channels. We must always comply with your request.

In cases where we are processing your personal data on the basis of our contract with you, public task or for a legitimate interest, you can ask us to stop for reasons connected to your individual situation. We must then do so unless we believe we have an overriding reason to continue processing your personal data, if this is the case we will advise you of the reason.

Here are all our Privacy statements, detailing how we collect & use your personal data depending on your relationship with the University of Salford. If you have any questions regarding the statements please get in touch with the person/department listed in the relevant Notice.

To protect the confidentiality of your information, we will ask you to verify your identity before proceeding with any request you make under a Privacy Notice. If you have authorised a third party to submit a request on your behalf, we will ask them to prove they have your permission to act.

More information on how the University collects & uses personal information can be found in the [Notification](https://ico.org.uk/ESDWebPages/Entry/Z5907252) made to the ICO [**https://ico.org.uk/ESDWebPages/Entry/Z469563X**](https://ico.org.uk/ESDWebPages/Entry/Z469563X) or in the relevant Privacy Notice.

## Data Protection

The GDPR, building on previous data protection legislation, gives people the right to know what information is held about them & requires the University to ensure that personal information relating to living individuals is handled properly, held in confidence & is protected from inappropriate disclosure to third parties.

It provides a comprehensive & modern framework for data protection in the UK. and will give people more control over use of their data, provide new rights to move or delete personal data & impose stronger sanctions for malpractice.

Everyone who collects & manages personal information at the University of Salford must do so in a way that complies with the University's Policy on Data Protection, **<https://www.salford.ac.uk/__data/assets/pdf_file/0005/316733/DataProtectionPolicyV2.0.pdf> **the 6 principles, and the new Individual Rights under GDPR.

## Cookies

Cookies are tiny text files stored on your computer when you visit certain web pages, websites use them to keep track of what you have in your basket, what you are looking at & to remember you when you return to the site.

Please note that cookies can't harm your computer. We don't store personally identifiable information in cookies we create, but we do use encrypted information gathered from them to help improve your experience of the site. For example, they help us to identify & resolve errors, or to determine the most visited pages.

We will have a full list of the cookies we deploy on the University of Salford website as soon as possible.

When you visit [www.salford.ac.uk](https://www.salford.ac.uk/) you may notice some Cookies that aren't related to the University. If you go on to a web page that contains embedded content, for example from YouTube, you may be sent Cookies from these websites. We don't control the setting of these Cookies, so please check the third-party websites for more information about their cookies & how to manage them.

You can manage Cookies on the site or at a browser level. 

For information about managing cookies in your browser, please refer to [www.aboutcookies.org.uk/managing-cookies](http://www.aboutcookies.org.uk/managing-cookies).

Some sites offer the opportunity to refuse cookies for that site. However please be aware that websites use Cookies to improve experience whilst browsing & for certain functionality, so if you disable Cookies you might not be able to use all functions on the site.

## Contact/Complaint

### How to get in Touch With Us

Advice & guidance on aspects of data protection within the University of Salford is available from the Information Governance Team, they can be contacted email at: [foi@salford.ac.uk](mailto:foi@salford.ac.uk).

Our postal address is:

Information Governance Officer  
Legal and Governance Directorate  
Maxwell 6th floor  
University of Salford  
M5 4WT

### If You Have a Complaint

If you feel that your data has not been handled correctly, or you are unhappy with our response to any requests you have made to us regarding the use of your personal data, please get in touch with the contact listed in the relevant Privacy Notice. If you wish to escalate any issue or complaint further please contact:

Data Protection Officer  
Legal and Governance Directorate  
Maxwell 6th floor  
University of Salford  
M5 4WT

Additionally, you have the right to lodge a complaint with the Information Commissioner’s Office (“ICO”)

You can contact them by calling [0303 123 1113](tel:03031231113) or go online to [www.ico.org.uk/concerns](http://www.ico.org.uk/concerns) (opens in a new window; please note we can't be responsible for the content of external websites)

If you are based outside the UK, you have the right to lodge your complaint with the relevant data protection regulator in your country of residence.
